Guide to the Nuclear Free America Records 1945-2003
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Nuclear Free America Records
1945-2003
1983-1995
Nuclear Free America (Organization)
MSS NFA
19.00 cubic feet, including 50 photographs and 26 VHS tapes 20 boxes, including 1 oversize box
Special Collections and Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/findingaids
The Nuclear Free America Records document the activities of this nonprofit resource center throughout the lifetime of the organization. Nuclear Free America facilitated a worldwide antinuclear movement to create "nuclear free zones" (NFZs) or communities where nuclear production, testing, waste, and transportation activities were banned. During its 15 years of operation, more than 200 NFZ declarations were passed by 4,500 local governments in 26 nations worldwide. The collection includes administrative records, records of nuclear free zone declarations by localities around the world, and extensive files related to affiliated antinuclear organizations.
Historical Note:
Nuclear Free America (NFA) was an international clearinghouse and resource center founded in 1982, primarily to serve communities in the United States wishing to declare themselves nuclear free zones (NFZs) as part of a worldwide movement. NFA closed its doors in 1997. During its fifteen years of operation, more than 200 NFZ declarations passed within the territory of the United States, as part of over 4,500 declarations passed by local governments in 26 nations worldwide.
Local NFZs were established in solidarity with international treaties covering the Antarctic, Outer Space, the Sea-Bed, Latin America and the Caribbean, Africa, Southeast Asia, the Pacific Islands, and Central Asia.
NFA, headquartered in Baltimore, Maryland, and, from 1993-1997, with a second office in Salem, Oregon, served as the US affiliate and United Nations representative of the International Secretariat of the Nuclear Free Zone Local Authorities. Primary organizers were Chuck Johnson and Albert Donnay.
The early focus of NFA was assisting mostly symbolic declarations against nuclear weapons - part of national and international efforts to protest Cold War nuclear weapons policies of the US and its allies.
After the Cold War, fears about nuclear weapons waned, but concerns about storage of nuclear waste from more than 100 commercial nuclear power plants grew as proposed nuclear waste sites proliferated throughout the country. NFA assisted communities in developing NFZ declarations that served as symbolic buffers - or real barriers in the case of laws passed by sovereign Native American Nations.
To assist several communities that wished to end investment or purchase from nuclear weapons manufacturers, NFA researchers, working with Eagle Eye Publishers, developed an annual database of US nuclear weapons contractors that eventually expanded to include several specific definitions of weapons production and was used as the definitive measure by socially responsible investment companies and others to boycott weapons makers. This service continued in an attenuated form until 2003.
Donnay, Albert, 1958-; Johnson, Charles K.
Born digital.; Photographic prints.; Video recordings (physical artifacts)
Antinuclear movement.; Nuclear disarmament.; Nuclear energy--Environmental aspects--United States.; Nuclear industry.; Nuclear nonproliferation.; Nuclear weapons plants--Environmental aspects--United States.; Nuclear weapons--Moral and ethical aspects--United States.; Nuclear weapons--Social aspects.; Nuclear-weapon-free zones.; Radioactive waste disposal.
Civic Activism; Energy Production; International Relations; Native Americans; Nuclear Weapons and Testing; Science; Technology; Alaska; California; Idaho; Montana; Oregon; Washington; Artifacts; Electronic Records; Moving Imagaes; Photographs
Chuck Johnson and Albert Donnay donated these materials to the Special Collections and Archives Research Center in 2016.
The collection is open for research, excepting Series 9: Electronic Records, which contains unprocessed material.
The Ava Helen and Linus Pauling Papers, Series 12: Peace, documents the Paulings' decades of antinuclear activism in detail. The History of Atomic Energy rare book collection has strengths in activist movements, as well as materials on radioactive waste disposal, nuclear energy, and nuclear weapons production. The David Marcus Letters show the effects of a smaller activist effort. The Paul J. Persiani Papers, Series 3 is comprised of a small group of materials related to Persiani's work on the Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty (START), which sought to place limits on the development and stockpiling of nuclear arms by the United States and the USSR. The Chih H. Wang Papers include materials on anti-nuclear campaigns in Series 6.
Some materials in this collection were exposed to water damage and dusty conditions; all materials in the collection have been cleaned and some materials were photocopied and discarded.
The Nuclear Free America Records are divided into 9 series: Series 1: Administrative Records, 1981-2000; Series 2: Nuclear Free Zones Project, 1981-1995; Series 3: Weapons Maker Database, 1986-2001; Series 4: Other Initiatives and Projects, 1979-1995; Series 5: Related Organizations, 1983-2000; Series 6: Subject Files, 1988-2000; Series 7: Artifacts and Memorabilia, 1945-1996; Series 8: Video Recordings, 1979-2003; Series 9: Electronic Records, circa 1985-1995.
Series 1 is further divided into 4 subseries: Subseries 1: General; Subseries 2: Grant Funding; Subseries 3: Fundraising Initiatives; Subseries 4: Conferences.
Series 2 is further divided into 4 subseries: Subseries 1: Project Records; Subseries 2: United States Zones; Subseries 3: Native Lands (United States) Zones; and Subseries 4: International Zones. These records are arranged geographically, alphabetically by state, and localities within each state.
The Nuclear Free America Records document the activities of this nonprofit antinuclear organization during its most active years.
Series 1: Administrative Records covers all general operational functions of Nuclear Free America (NFA) including staffing, administration, finance, outreach and promotion, and organizational contacts. Series 1 is further divided into 4 subseries. Subseries 1: General includes financial records, meeting minutes, and staffing records. Subseries 2: Grant Funding and Subseries 3: Fundraising demonstrate the funding efforts by this small organization through different means, including local initiatives and private donations. Subseries 4: Conferences contains several folders of meeting minutes from the Nuclear Free Local Authorities international conferences, which shed further light on NFA's work.
Series 2: Nuclear Free Zones contains the majority of materials in the collection and documents the efforts by NFA to create "nuclear free zones" (NFZs), or communities where nuclear production, testing, waste, and transportation activities were banned. The series is arranged geographically and contains documentation of NFA's work with each locality or community organizing toward an NFZ declaration. While some efforts were ultimately unsuccessful, most declarations happened successfully due to the liaising and guidance provided by Nuclear Free America. Some communities, including those in New York, Ohio, and California used the NFZ effort to successfully protest nearby nuclear waste disposal plans. Within this series, Subseries 3: Native Lands contains important documentation of efforts by tribal leaders to eradicate nuclear presence from various native reservations. Of particular note are materials including correspondence, meeting minutes, and legal documents related to NFA's partnership with the National Environmental Coalition of Native Americans to help fight the U. S. Department of Energy's plan to site 'temporary' high-level radioactive waste dumps on native lands. The international zones represented in Subseries 4 include documentation of efforts by NFA to include nuclear issues in international discussions related to protecting the Arctic and other remote regions.
Series 3: Weapons-Maker Database shows how NFA became the sole source of information on U.S. companies that make or support nuclear weapons, in order to support socially conscious investing, boycott efforts, and divestment campaigns. The Weapons Maker Database and its various datasets were provided to buyers from 1990 to 1995 and the series contains client information sheets, compiled lists, and correspondence. Series 4: Other Initiatives and Projects demonstrates fundraising and other outreach efforts undertaken by the organization, including significant boycotting activity and documentaries. The collected materials in Series 5: Related Organizations offer a window into both national and international antinuclear and peace activism during the late 1980s and early 1990s, and show grassroots activist efforts addressing a number of nuclear concerns through publications, activities, events, and outreach. The similar materials in Series 6 were grouped by NFA according to topic rather than organization. Series 7: Artifacts and Memorabilia contains ephemera such as stickers, buttons, and placards from a wide body of antinuclear events and organizations. Series 8: Video Recordings contains over 20 VHS tapes about a variety of topics, including the Trojan Nuclear Plant in Oregon and environmental impacts on the Columbia River. Series 9: Electronic Records contains various electronic formats that are not currently processed and inaccessible to researchers.
- Administrative Records, 1981-2000; Series 1
  Series 1 documents the administrative activities of the organization, and includes summary reports, financial records, funding proposals, grant applications, contact lists, and outreach records. Evidence of the organization’s donor outreach activities, including mailer campaigns and donor approaches, is ample in this series. Notable in this series are records of several events sponsored jointly with other local anti-nuclear nonprofit organizations, including two dance marathon fundraisers, which show the organization’s network and community reach. Also notable is an incomplete run of The New Abolitionist, the newspaper produced by Nuclear Free America from the late 1980s to the mid 1990s. Content includes reports from national and international Nuclear Free Zones, progress reports from campaigns underway, and related nuclear and disarmament news.
  - General, 1983-2000
    - Administrative notes, undated (Box-folder 1.01)
    - Board meeting minutes, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 1.02)
    - Correspondence, 1983-2000 (Box-folder 1.03)
    - Financial records - banking and investment accounts, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 1.04)
    - Financial records - income and expenses, 1987-1995 (Box-folder 1.05)
    - Financial records - operating expenses and agreements, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 1.06)
    - Program activity reports, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 1.07)
    - Outreach and promotion - advertising and news coverage, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 1.08)
    - Outreach and promotion - direct mail campaigns, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 1.09)
    - Outreach and promotion - direct mail campaigns, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 1.10)
    - Outreach and promotion - direct mail campaigns, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 1.11)
    - Outreach and promotion - drafts and samples, 1984-1995 (Box-folder 1.12)
    - Outreach and promotion - literature and articles, 1987-1995 (Box-folder 1.13)
    - Outreach and promotion - mailers and brochures, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 1.14)
    - Outreach and promotion - non-NFA samples, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 1.15)
    - Outreach and promotion - press releases, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 1.16)
    - Outreach and promotion - The New Abolitionist, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 1.17)
    - Professional contacts, 1989-2000 (Box-folder 1.18)
    - Staffing, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 1.19)
    - Tax and trademark records, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 1.20)
  - Grant Funding, 1981-1998
    - 1983 general funding proposal (Box-folder 1.21)
    - 1984 general funding proposal (Box-folder 1.22)
    - 1985 general funding proposal (Box-folder 1.23)
    - 1987 general funding proposal (Box-folder 1.24)
    - 1989 general funding proposal (Box-folder 1.25)
    - 1990 general funding proposal (Box-folder 1.26)
    - Sample funding proposals, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 1.27)
    - American Friends Service Committee, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1.28)
    - Boehm Foundation, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 1.29)
    - C.S. Fund, 1983-1993 (Box-folder 1.30)
    - Capp Street Foundation, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 1.31)
    - CarEth Foundation, 1983-1993 (Box-folder 1.32)
    - Citizen Action for Lasting Security, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 1.33)
    - Earth Care Paper, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 1.34)
    - Exchange Project, 1984 (Box-folder 1.35)
    - Grant-making organizations: M, 1982-1993 (Box-folder 2.01)
    - Grant-making organizations: N, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 2.02)
    - Grant-making organizations: O, undated (Box-folder 2.03)
    - Grant-making organizations: P, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 2.04)
    - Grant-making organizations: R, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 2.05)
    - Grant-making organizations: S, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 2.06)
    - Grant-making organizations: T, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 2.07)
    - Grant-making organizations: U, 1984-1996 (Box-folder 2.08)
    - Grant-making organizations: W, 1986-1991 (Box-folder 2.09)
    - Grant-making organizations: Y, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 2.10)
    - Grant-making organizations and private donor contact lists, undated (Box-folder 2.11)
    - Grant and donation income records, 1982-1998 (Box-folder 2.12)
  - Fundraising Initiatives, 1983-1995
    - Affinity fund profit sharing, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 2.13)
    - Corporate Partners for Peace campaign, 1995 (Box-folder 2.14)
    - Fundraising ideas and non-NFA fundraising materials, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 2.15)
    - Fundraising resources, 1984-1993 (Box-folder 2.16)
    - Give Peace a Dance, undated (Box-folder 2.17)
    - Give Peace a Dance, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2.18)
    - Give Peace a Dance, 1985 (Box-folder 2.19)
    - Home phonebanking project, undated (Box-folder 2.20)
    - Private donors, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 2.21)
    - Rock Against the Clock, 1985 (Box-folder 2.22)
    - Save Our Cities March, 1992 (Box-folder 2.23)
  - Conferences, 1982-1995
    - 1st International Conference of Local Authority Nuclear Free Zones. Manchester, England, 1984 (Box-folder 2.24)
    - 5th International conference of Nuclear Free Zone Local Authorities. Glasgow, Scotland, 1990 (Box-folder 2.25)
    - 5th International conference of Nuclear Free Zone Local Authorities. Glasgow, Scotland, 1990 (Box-folder 2.26)
    - 6th International Conference on Nuclear Free Zone Local Authorities. Kanagawa, Japan., 1992 (Box-folder 2.27)
    - 6th International Conference on Nuclear Free Zone Local Authorities. Kanagawa, Japan, 1992 (Box-folder 3.01)
    - 6th International Conference on Nuclear Free Zone Local Authorities. Kanagawa, Japan, 1992 (Box-folder 3.02)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authorities, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 3.03)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authorities Meeting Minutes, 1982 (Box-folder 3.04)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authorities Meeting Minutes, 1983 (Box-folder 3.05)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authorities Meeting Minutes, 1984 (Box-folder 3.06)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authorities Meeting Minutes, 1985 (Box-folder 3.07)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authorities Meeting Minutes, 1986 (Box-folder 3.08)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authorities Meeting Minutes, 1987 (Box-folder 3.09)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authority International Secretariat Meeting. Amadora, Portugal, 1991 (Box-folder 3.10)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authority International Secretariat, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 3.11)
    - Nuclear Free Local Authority International Secretariat, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 3.12)
    - United Nations 3rd Special Session on Disarmament (SSOD-III), 1988 (Box-folder 3.13)
    - United States Nuclear Free Zone Association Executive Committee Meeting. Washington D.C., 1990 (Box-folder 3.14)
    - Second Global Radiation Victims Conference. Berlin, Germany, 1992 (Box-folder 3.15)
    - 51st Annual Convention of the National Congress of American Indians, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 3.16)
    - Environmental Justice Symposium. St. John's University, 1994 (Box-folder 3.17)
    - Miscellaneous conferences, undated (Box-folder 3.18)
- Nuclear Free Zones Project, 1981-1995; Series 2
  Series 2 documents the primary campaign of Nuclear Free America, to create Nuclear Free Zones around the world. Grouped by geographical area, the files in this series show how NFA worked with grassroots activists at each locality to advance this goal. In addition to correspondence with these activists and data sheets detailing the nature of the local campaign, these files include fundraising materials, promotional materials for the campaign such as event flyers, advertising posters, and petitions; local news and press coverage, including newspapers and clippings, letters to the editor, and editorials; text of proposed ordinances and resolutions; correspondence with local authorities; handwritten notes; literature from pronuclear organizations and individuals; city council agendas and minutes; minutes and related materials from partner organizations; speeches, and more. These document the organizing activities at the grassroots level and can be used to show how the presence of nuclear materials, waste, or energy production affected specific localities and communities.
  - Project Records, 1988-1990
    - International contacts, undated (Box-folder 3.19)
    - News coverage and reference materials, undated (Box-folder 3.20)
    - NFZ campaign lists, undated (Box-folder 3.21)
    - NFZ Divestiture Subcommittee, undated (Box-folder 3.22)
    - Organization literature, undated (Box-folder 3.23)
    - Organizing packet, undated (Box-folder 3.24)
    - Project files, undated (Box-folder 4.01)
    - Project files, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 4.02)
  - United States Zones, 1982-1995
    - Alabama, 1988 (Box-folder 4.03)
    - Alaska, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 4.04)
    - Alaska, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 4.05)
    - Alaska - Greater Juneau, 1988 (Box-folder 4.06)
    - Alaska - Kenai Peninsula - Homer, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 4.07)
    - Alaska - Ketchikan Gateway, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 4.08)
    - Arizona, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 4.09)
    - Arkansas, 1985 (Box-folder 4.10)
    - California, undated (Box-folder 4.11)
    - California (counties), 1984-1987 (Box-folder 4.12)
    - California - Alameda County, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 4.13)
    - California - Alameda County, undated (Box-folder 4.14)
    - California - Alameda County - Berkeley, undated (Box-folder 4.15)
    - California - Alameda County - Oakland, 1989 (Box-folder 4.16)
    - California - Alameda County - Oakland, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 4.17)
    - California - Alameda County - Oakland, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 4.18)
    - California - Butte County, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 4.19)
    - California - Fresno County, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 5.01)
    - California - Humboldt County, undated (Box-folder 5.02)
    - California - Los Angeles County, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 5.03)
    - California - Los Angeles County - Santa Monica, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 5.04)
    - California - Marin County, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 5.05)
    - California - Marin County, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 5.06)
    - California - Marin County, 1984-1991 (Box-folder 5.07)
    - California - Mendocino County, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 5.08)
    - California - Napa County, undated (Box-folder 5.09)
    - California - San Bernardino County, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 5.10)
    - California - San Diego County, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 5.11)
    - California - San Francisco County, undated (Box-folder 5.12)
    - California - San Francisco County, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 5.13)
    - California - San Luis Obispo County, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 5.14)
    - California - San Mateo County, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 5.15)
    - California - Santa Barbara County, undated (Box-folder 5.16)
    - California - Santa Clara County, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 5.17)
    - California - Santa Clara County - Palo Alto, undated (Box-folder 5.18)
    - California - Santa Cruz County, undated (Box-folder 5.19)
    - California - Sonoma County, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 5.20)
    - California - Ventura County, undated (Box-folder 6.01)
    - California - Yolo County - Davis, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 6.02)
    - Colorado, undated (Box-folder 6.03)
    - Connecticut, undated (Box-folder 6.04)
    - Connecticut, 1986-1993 (Box-folder 6.05)
    - Delaware, undated (Box-folder 6.06)
    - Florida, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 6.07)
    - Georgia, undated (Box-folder 6.08)
    - Hawaii - Hawaii County, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 6.09)
    - Hawaii - Kauai County, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 6.10)
    - Hawaii - Maui County, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 6.11)
    - Idaho, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 6.12)
    - Illinois, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 6.13)
    - Illinois - Cook County - Chicago, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 6.14)
    - Indiana, undated (Box-folder 6.15)
    - Iowa, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 6.16)
    - Kansas, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 6.17)
    - Kentucky, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 6.18)
    - Louisiana, undated (Box-folder 6.19)
    - Maine, 1985-1995 (Box-folder 6.20)
    - Maryland (counties), 1982-1988 (Box-folder 6.21)
    - Maryland - Calvert County, 1993 (Box-folder 6.22)
    - Maryland - Montgomery County - Garrett Park, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 6.23)
    - Maryland - Montgomery County - Takoma Park, 1986-1992 (Box-folder 6.24)
    - Maryland - Montgomery County - Takoma Park, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 6.25)
    - Maryland - Montgomery County - Takoma Park, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 7.01)
    - Maryland - Baltimore, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 7.02)
    - Maryland - Baltimore, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 7.03)
    - Maryland - Baltimore, undated (Box-folder 7.04)
    - Maryland - Baltimore, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 7.05)
    - Maryland - Baltimore, undated (Box-folder 7.06)
    - Maryland - Baltimore - City Council, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 7.07)
    - Maryland - Baltimore - City League of Environmental Voters, undated (Box-folder 7.08)
    - Maryland - Baltimore - Ordinance, 1992 (Box-folder 7.09)
    - Maryland - Baltimore - South African uranium, 1982-1988 (Box-folder 7.10)
    - Massachusetts, undated (Box-folder 7.11)
    - Massachusetts, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 7.12)
    - Massachusetts - Barnstable County, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 7.13)
    - Massachusetts - Barnstable County, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 7.14)
    - Massachusetts - Franklin County, 1983 (Box-folder 7.15)
    - Massachusetts - Hampshire County, 1984 (Box-folder 7.16)
    - Massachusetts - Middlesex County, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 7.17)
    - Massachusetts - Middlesex County - Cambridge, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 8.01)
    - Massachusetts - Middlesex County - Cambridge, undated (Box-folder 8.02)
    - Massachusetts - Middlesex County - Cambridge - Citizens Against Research Bans, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 8.03)
    - Michigan, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 8.04)
    - Minnesota, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 8.05)
    - Missouri, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 8.06)
    - Mississippi, undated (Box-folder 8.07)
    - Montana, undated (Box-folder 8.08)
    - Nebraska, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 8.09)
    - Nevada, undated (Box-folder 8.10)
    - Nevada, undated (Box-folder 8.11)
    - New Hampshire, undated (Box-folder 8.12)
    - New Jersey, undated (Box-folder 8.13)
    - New Jersey, 1982-1988 (Box-folder 8.14)
    - New Jersey - Sussex County, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 8.15)
    - New Jersey - Union County, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 8.16)
    - New Mexico, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 8.17)
    - New York, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 8.18)
    - New York, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8.19)